A Guide to the Virginia Military Institute Records, 1837-1884
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Military Institute Records, 1837-1884
The Library of Virginia
APA 124
.25 cf (5 in.)
Auditor of Public Accounts
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information is available.
Biographical Information
On 22 March 1836 the General Assembly ordered that a military school be established at the Lexington Arsenal. The governor chose a board of visitors who annually audited the accounts of the school treasurer, inspected the condition of the school and the arms at the arsenal, and reported to the governor. When the student body grew to a sufficient size, they were formed into corps for the protection of the arsenal, and the public guard was disbanded. On 29 March 1839 the General Assembly passed an act naming the military school at Lexington the Virginia Military Institute. In subsequent acts the General Assembly appropriated funds to run the school and construct new buildings.
Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence, financial accounts, reports, extracts from minutes, and warrants for payment. Of particular interest is the Board of Visitors Annual Report from 1849. The report covers the expenses for the institution and its operations including food, weapons, instruction, buildings, and subsistence. It also details an investigation into a fire that occurred in March of that year and the fire and safety measures in place.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by item.
Contents List
- Virginia Military Institute Records, 1837-1884. (Box 1)
  - Accounts, 1855. (Folder 1)
  - Annual Report of the Board of Visitors, 1848-1849. (Folder 2)
    - Abstract of Annual Return
    - Armory
    - Board of Visitor's Annual Report
    - Board of Visitor's Special Report
    - Buildings
    - Committee on Finances
    - Committee on Instruction
    - Ex-Cadet Dues
    - Finance Statement
    - Merit Roll of Cadets
    - Mess Hall
    - Proceedings of Court of Enquiry of Fire
    - Quarter Master's Department
    - Subsistence Department
    - Superintendent's Report
    - Tailor's Department
    - Treasurer's Account
  - Extract from the Records of the Board of Visitors, 1884. (Folder 3)
  - Warrants, 1837-1856. (Folder 4)
  - Warrants, 1858-1859, 1861, 1864-1865. (Folder 5)